<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Home on Ko Arimatsu web page</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Home on Ko Arimatsu web page</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>jp</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>所属・職位</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/about/current-affiliation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/about/current-affiliation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;京都大学 白眉センター・特定助教&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>研究テーマ</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/about/research-topics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/about/research-topics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;恒星掩蔽観測による太陽系外縁天体・オールト雲の探査&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;外惑星衝突閃光観測による太陽系外縁微小天体の探査&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;可視小型・高速観測システムの開発と応用&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>学歴</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/about/education/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/about/education/</guid>
      <description>&lt;dl class=&#34;edu&#34;&gt;&#xA; &lt;dt&gt;2006年3月&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;群馬県立前橋高等学校 卒業&lt;/dd&gt;  &#xA; &lt;dt&gt;2006年4月&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;東京大学 教養学部 理科一類 入学&lt;/dd&gt; &#xA; &lt;dt&gt;2010年3月&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;東京大学 理学部 天文学科 卒業&lt;/dd&gt; &#xA;&lt;dt&gt;2010年4月&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;東京大学大学院 理学系研究科 天文学専攻 修士課程 入学&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;  &lt;dt&gt;2012年3月&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;同 修士課程 修了&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;  &lt;dt&gt;2012年4月&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;東京大学大学院 天文学専攻 博士課程 進学&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;  &lt;dt&gt;2015年3月&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;同 博士課程 修了／博士（理学）取得&lt;/dd&gt; &#xA;&lt;/dl&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>職歴</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/about/employment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/about/employment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;dl class=&#34;edu&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;dt&gt;2015年4月&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;国立天文台 天文情報センター／日本学術振興会 特別研究員（PD）〔〜2018年3月〕&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;  &lt;dt&gt;2018年9月&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;京都大学 大学院理学研究科 附属天文台 研究員〔〜2020年12月〕&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;  &lt;dt&gt;2021年1月&lt;/dt&gt;&lt;dd&gt;京都大学 白眉センター 特定助教〔在職中〕&lt;/dd&gt;&#xA;&lt;/dl&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>日本語訳監修, 『おやすみのあとで』(書籍, 文: アニタ・ガネリ, 絵:シャーロット・ペッ パー, 訳: 刈茅 由美), 世界文化社</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/g-2025-g1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/g-2025-g1/</guid>
      <description>ノンフィクション科学絵本(原題: Through the NightSky)の翻訳を監修した。監修では天文学に関す る用語が正確に翻訳されていることを確認するとともに、内容に関するファクトチェックと最新情報への更新作業をおこなった。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>天体写真提供, 『天文を愛した文学者たち』, 科学雑誌 Newton 2025年5月号, ニュートンプレス</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2025-h16-newton-2025-5-2025-3-oases/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2025-h16-newton-2025-5-2025-3-oases/</guid>
      <description>OASESプロジェクトがモデルとなった伊与原新氏の小説『オオルリ流星群』の解説画像として、 OASES観測システムと天の川を撮影した写真が採用された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>科学イラスト提供, 『よくわかる国語の学習3年生』(書籍, 学校用学習教材), 明治図書出版</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2025-h15-3-2025-4-98943-torifune-2-cg/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2025-h15-3-2025-4-98943-torifune-2-cg/</guid>
      <description>作成した小惑星(98943) Torifuneにフライバイする小惑星探査機『はやぶさ2』のCGイラス トが、『はやぶさ2』の説明画像として採用された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>科学イラスト提供, 『太陽系の謎を追え！　小さな望遠鏡による大きな発見に期待！』, 子供の科学 2025年5月号, 誠文堂新光社</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2025-2025-5-2025-4-oases/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2025-2025-5-2025-4-oases/</guid>
      <description>特集内でOASESプロジェクトが紹介され、解説イラストとして太陽系外縁部に存在する小天体のCG イラストが採用された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The  OASES  Project:  Exploring  the  Outer  Solar  System  through  Stellar Occultation with Amateur-Class Telescopes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-the-oases-project-exploring-the-outer-solar-system-through-stellar-occultation-w/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2025-the-oases-project-exploring-the-outer-solar-system-through-stellar-occultation-w/</guid>
      <description>The exploration of kilometre-sized trans-Neptunian objects (TNOs) is one of the ultimate goals in the search for the origin and evolution of the Solar System. However, such exploration is challenging because these small bodies are too faint to be directly detected. One potential avenue for detecting and investigating small and faint TNOs is the monitoring of stellar occultation events. This paper reviews the concept and methodology of monitoring observations of stellar occultations by small, unidentified TNOs, focusing on our observational programme, Organized Autotelescopes for Serendipitous Event Survey (OASES). OASES aims to detect and investigate stellar occultations by unidentified TNOs using multiple amateur-sized telescopes equipped with commercial complementary metal-oxide-semiconductor (CMOS) cameras. Through the monitoring observations conducted so far, OASES has found one possible occultation event by a kilometre-sized TNO. The paper also discusses future developments of the OASES project and deliberates on the potential of movie observations in expanding the frontiers of outer Solar System research.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け雑誌記事執筆,『動画天文学が解き明かす未開の太陽系 ―― はやぶさ 2 次期フライバイターゲッ ト「トリフネ」 形状決定を例に』, 科学 2025年2月号, 岩波書店</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2025-f11/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2025-f11/</guid>
      <description>小惑星(98943) Torifuneの掩蔽観測結果について、一般向けの科学雑誌に記事を執筆し、研究成果を紹介・解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け講演, 『OASES(オアシズ)とPONCOTS(ポンコツ): 小さな望遠鏡が解明する新しい 太陽系』, 日本スペースガード協会関西支部 第59回公開講演会, 神戸市教育会館(兵庫県神戸市)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2025-c20-oases-poncots/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2025-c20-oases-poncots/</guid>
      <description>OASESプロジェクトおよびPONCOTSプロジェクトとこれまで得られてきた研究成果について、一般の参加者に向けて講演をおこなった。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Candidate  Distant  Trans-Neptunian  Objects  Detected  by  the  New  Horizons  Subaru TNO Survey</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-candidate-distant-trans-neptunian-objects-detected-by-the-new-horizons-subaru-tn/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-candidate-distant-trans-neptunian-objects-detected-by-the-new-horizons-subaru-tn/</guid>
      <description>We report the detection of 239 trans-Neptunian objects discovered through the ongoing New Horizons survey for distant minor bodies being performed with the Hyper Suprime-Cam mosaic imager on the Subaru Telescope. These objects were discovered in images acquired with either the r2 or the recently commissioned EB-gri filter using shift and stack routines. Due to the extremely high stellar density of the search region downstream of the spacecraft, new machine learning techniques had to be developed to manage the extremely high false-positive rate of bogus candidates produced from the shift and stack routines. We report discoveries as faint as r2 ∼ 26.5. We highlight an overabundance of objects found at heliocentric distances R ≳ 70 au compared to expectations from modeling of the known outer solar system. If confirmed, these objects betray the presence of a heretofore-unrecognized abundance of distant objects that can help explain a number of other observations that otherwise remain at odds with the known Kuiper Belt, including detections of serendipitous stellar occultations, and recent results from the Student Dust Counter on board the New Horizons spacecraft.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>天体写真提供・解説, 『京大の屋上で撮影した「中秋の名月」が美しすぎると話題』, まいどなニュース</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2024-h14-2024-9-poncots/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2024-h14-2024-9-poncots/</guid>
      <description>PONCOTS観測中に撮影し、公式SNSにアップロードした満月の画像についてインタビューを受け、撮影写真が解説付きで掲載された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での研究成果解説, 『小惑星の大気圏突入を予測、石垣島天文台で火球観測...「地球防衛の予行演習」』, 読売新聞</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2024-e38/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2024-e38/</guid>
      <description>2024年9月に石垣島天文台にて国内で初めて観測に成功した、事前に発見された小惑星2024 RW1の大気圏突入についてインタビューを受け、解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ニュース番組出演・研究成果解説, 『「はやぶさ2」が目指す小惑星「細長いだ円形」と推定』, NHK, NHKニュースただいま佐賀</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2024-e37-2-nhk-nhk-2024-8-cid/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2024-e37-2-nhk-nhk-2024-8-cid/</guid>
      <description>恒星掩蔽観測によるはやぶさ2探査機の次期フライバイターゲット小惑星(98943) Torifuneの形状推定の研究成果についてインタビューを受け、解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での研究成果解説, 『「はやぶさ2」が次に向かう小惑星、落花生に似た形、アマ天文家も解明に一役』, 産経新聞</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2024-e34-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2024-e34-2/</guid>
      <description>恒星掩蔽観測によるはやぶさ2探査機の次期フライバイターゲット小惑星(98943) Torifuneの形状推定の研究成果についてインタビューを受け、解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での研究成果解説, 『はやぶさ2が向かう小惑星は細長い「ピーナツ形」、アマ チュア天文家の観測データから判明』, 読売新聞</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2024-e36-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2024-e36-2/</guid>
      <description>恒星掩蔽観測によるはやぶさ2探査機の次期フライバイターゲット小惑星(98943) Torifuneの形状推定の研究成果についてインタビューを受け、解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>通信社配信記事中での研究成果解説, 『はやぶさ2、目的地は細長い形状 次なる探査の小 惑星、京大解析』, 共同通信</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2024-e35-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2024-e35-2/</guid>
      <description>恒星掩蔽観測によるはやぶさ2探査機の次期フライバイターゲット小惑星(98943) Torifuneの形状推定の研究成果についてインタビューを受け、解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffraction  modelling  of  a  2023  March  5  stellar occultation  by  subkilometer-sized  asteroid  (98943)  2001  CC21</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-diffraction-modelling-of-a-2023-march-5-stellar-occultation-by-subkilometer-size/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-diffraction-modelling-of-a-2023-march-5-stellar-occultation-by-subkilometer-size/</guid>
      <description>We present an analysis of a stellar occultation event caused by a near-Earth asteroid (98943) 2001 CC21, an upcoming flyby target in the Hayabusa2 extended mission, on 2023 March 5. To determine the asteroid’s shape from diffraction-affected light curves accurately, we developed a novel data-reduction technique named the Diffracted Occultation’s United Simulator for Highly Informative Transient Explorations (DOUSHITE). Using DOUSHITE-generated synthetic models, we derived constraints on (98943) 2001 CC21’s shadow shape from the single-chord occultation data. Our results suggest a significant elongation of the shadow with an axis ratio of b/a = 0.37 ± 0.09 ⁠. This shape could be crucial for planning Hayabusa2’s high-speed flyby to optimise the limited imaging opportunities.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け講演, 『木星の閃光はわれわれに何を伝えるのか: SL9以降もつづく木星への天体衝突』, 日本スペースガード協会アステロイドデー・スペシャルトーク, 中央大学附属中学校・高等学校(東京都小金井市)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2024-c19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2024-c19/</guid>
      <description>PONCOTSによる木星衝突閃光の観測について、一般向けに講演をおこなった。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical  Variability  of  Blazars  in  the  Tomo-e  Gozen  Northern  Sky  Transient Survey</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-optical-variability-of-blazars-in-the-tomo-e-gozen-northern-sky-transient-survey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-optical-variability-of-blazars-in-the-tomo-e-gozen-northern-sky-transient-survey/</guid>
      <description>We studied the optical variability of 241 BL Lacertae (BL Lacs) and 83 flat-spectrum radio quasars (FSRQs) from the 4LAC catalog using data from the Tomo-e Gozen Northern Sky Transient Survey, with ∼50 epochs per blazar on average. We excluded blazars whose optical variability may be underestimated due to the influence of their host galaxy based on their optical luminosity (LO). FSRQs with γ-ray photon index greater than 2.6 exhibit very low optical variability, and their distribution of standard deviation of repeated photometry is significantly different from that of the other FSRQs (Kolmogorov–Smirnov test p-value equal to 5 × 10−6). Among a sample of blazars at any particular cosmological epoch, those with lower γ-ray luminosity (Lγ) tend to have lower optical variability, and those FSRQs with a γ-ray photon index greater than 2.6 tend to have low Lγ. We also measured the structure function of optical variability and found that the amplitude of the structure function for FSRQs is higher than previously measured and higher than that of BL Lacs at multiple time lags. Additionally, the amplitude of the structure function of FSRQs with high γ-ray photon index is significantly lower than that of FSRQs with low γ-ray photon index. The structure function of FSRQs of high γ-ray photon index shows a characteristic timescale of more than 10 days, which may be the variability timescale of the accretion disk. In summary, we infer that the optical component of FSRQs with high γ-ray photon index may be dominated by the accretion disk.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け講演, 『OASES(オアシズ)とPONCOTS(ポンコツ): 小望遠鏡が解明する太陽系の新たなすがた』, 天文学普及講演会, 国立科学博物館(東京都台東区)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2024-c18-oases-poncots/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2024-c18-oases-poncots/</guid>
      <description>OASESプロジェクトおよびPONCOTSプロジェクトとこれまで得られてきた研究成果について、国立科学博物館に来場した一般の参加者に向けて講演をおこなった。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JASMINE: Near-Infrared Astrometry and Time Series Photometry Science</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/paper-37/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/paper-37/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cloud  reflection modelling  for  impact  flashes  on  Jupiter</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-cloud-reflection-modelling-for-impact-flashes-on-jupiter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-cloud-reflection-modelling-for-impact-flashes-on-jupiter/</guid>
      <description>Aims. We investigate the optical characteristics of flashes caused by the impact of metre- to decametre-sized outer Solar System objects on Jupiter, and the contributions of reflected light from surface clouds at visible wavelengths, in order to estimate more accurate bulk parameters, such as the luminous energy of the flash, the kinetic energy, the mass, and the size of the impact object.&#xA;Methods. Using the results of recent reflectivity studies of the Jovian surface, we developed a cloud reflection model that calculates the contribution of the reflected light relative to that directly from the flash. We compared the apparent luminous energy of the previously reported flashes with the expected cloud reflection contributions to obtain their revised bulk parameters.&#xA;Results. We find that cloud reflection contributions can make up to 200% of the flux directly from the flash, and thus can be the most significant uncertainty in the measurement of the bulk parameters. The reflection contributions strongly depend on wavelength. With our cloud reflection correction, we obtained revised bulk parameters for the previously reported flashes.&#xA;Conclusions. Our cloud reflection correction enables us to better understand the properties of objects impacting Jupiter and is crucial for ongoing detailed investigations using high-sensitivity and multi-wavelength observation systems, such as PONCOTS. It will also be useful for understanding other optical transients in Jupiter’s upper atmosphere, such as the recently discovered sprite-like events.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>天体写真提供,『こども宇宙科学』(書籍, 監修: 津村 耕司), 新星出版</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2023-h13/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2023-h13/</guid>
      <description>石垣島にて撮影に成功した全太陽系惑星の集合写真が、太陽系を解説するための資料画像として採用・掲載された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>テレビ番組出演,『小型望遠鏡で未開の領域を開拓!小天体観測/ 有松亘』, テレビ東京, 探求の階段</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2023-e33-2023-11-oases-poncots/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2023-e33-2023-11-oases-poncots/</guid>
      <description>OASESプロジェクトとPONCOTSプロジェクトのこれまでのあゆみや研究成果について取材を受け、ドキュメンタリー番組として放送された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A  search  for  extragalactic  fast  optical  transients  in  the Tomo-e  Gozen  high-cadence  survey</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-a-search-for-extragalactic-fast-optical-transients-in-the-tomo-e-gozen-high-cade/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2024-a-search-for-extragalactic-fast-optical-transients-in-the-tomo-e-gozen-high-cade/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け雑誌記事執筆, 木星にインパクトフラッシュ!』月刊星ナビ 2023年11月号, アストロアーツ</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2023-f10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2023-f10/</guid>
      <description>2023年8月に発生した木星衝突閃光について一般向けの科学雑誌に記事を執筆し、解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向けweb記事執筆, 『10例目、木星表面の閃光現象がとらえられる』アストロアーツWEBニュース, アストロアーツ</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2023-f9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2023-f9/</guid>
      <description>2023年8月に発生した木星衝突閃光について一般向けの科学webニュースサイトに記事を執筆し、解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での解説, “A Fireball Whacked Into Jupiter, and Astronomers Got It on Video”, The New York Times</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2023-e31-a-fireball-whacked-into-jupiter-and-astronomers-got-it-on-video-the-new-york/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2023-e31-a-fireball-whacked-into-jupiter-and-astronomers-got-it-on-video-the-new-york/</guid>
      <description>2023年8月に発生した木星衝突閃光についてインタビューを受け、解説した(英文記事)。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ニュース番組出演・解説,『木星に小天体衝突? ”発光現象” 新潟 天体観測愛好家が撮影 確 認は過去8例のみ 惑星の成り立ち解明に期待も 』, NHK, NHK 新潟ニュース610</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2023-e32-8-nhk-nhk-610-2023-9-2023-8/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2023-e32-8-nhk-nhk-610-2023-9-2023-8/</guid>
      <description>2023年8月に発生した木星衝突閃光についてインタビューを受け、解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での解説,『木星に天体衝突、地球なら都市ひとつ消滅レベル...日本各地で閃光 を観測』, 読売新聞</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2023-e29/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2023-e29/</guid>
      <description>2023年8月に発生した木星衝突閃光についてインタビューを受け、解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での解説,『木星の閃光、30〜40mの小天体が衝突か これまでで最も強い光 京大・有松特定助教が分析』, 河北新報</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2023-e30/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2023-e30/</guid>
      <description>2023年8月に発生した木星衝突閃光についてインタビューを受け、解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>高校生向け講演,『OASESとPONCOTS 小望遠鏡で明らかにする太陽系のすがた』, 第13回高校生天文活動発表会, 大阪教育大学 天王寺キャンパス(大阪府大阪市)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2023-c17-oases-poncots/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2023-c17-oases-poncots/</guid>
      <description>2023年7月、OASESプロジェクトおよびPONCOTSプロジェクトとこれまで得られてきた研究成果について、高校生に向けて講演をおこなった。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け記念講演,『彗星のふるさとを影と閃光で解明する: OASESとPONCOTSの挑戦』, 第51回 彗星会議, ライフパーク倉敷(岡山県倉敷市)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2023-c16/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2023-c16/</guid>
      <description>OASESプロジェクトおよびPONCOTSプロジェクトとこれまで得られてきた研究成果について、一般向けに記念講演をおこなった。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modelling  the optical  energy  profile  of  the  2021  October  Jupiter  impact  flash</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-modelling-the-optical-energy-profile-of-the-2021-october-jupiter-impact-flash/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2023-modelling-the-optical-energy-profile-of-the-2021-october-jupiter-impact-flash/</guid>
      <description>We have conducted numerical simulations to reproduce the observed optical energy profile of the 2021 October 15 (ut) impact flash on Jupiter, which was the largest and the most well-observed flash event detected by ground-based movie observations. The observed long-duration (∼5.5 s) optical emission can be reproduced by an impact of an object with an exceptionally small angle of entry relative to the horizontal. The apparent lack of the impact debris feature despite the large impact object was possibly due to the shallower angle of entry (≤12°), which resulted in the lower ablation per unit volume at altitudes higher than ⁠, and the volume densities of the ablated materials were too low to allow the debris particulates to coagulate. The absence of temporal methane absorption change in the observed flash spectrum is consistent with the best-fitting results. The model better fits the observed optical energy profile for weaker material (cometary and stony) cases than for metallic ones. Based on the simulation results, prospects for future observations of impact flashes are discussed.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>天体写真提供,『フォトサイエンス 地学図録』(書籍, 学校用学習教材), 数研出版</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2023-h12-2023-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2023-h12-2023-2/</guid>
      <description>石垣島にて撮影に成功した全太陽系惑星の集合写真が、太陽系を解説するための資料画像として採用・掲載された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>雑誌特集でのインタビュー・研究プロジェクト解説, 『【インタビュー】ニュースで話題に なったアノ人に直撃!「暇だから研究する」科学者が素朴に思っていること』, 月刊化学(雑誌)2023 年2月号, 化学同人</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2023-e28-2023-2-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2023-e28-2023-2-2023/</guid>
      <description>雑誌の特集記事としてOASESプロジェクトおよびPONCOTSプロジェクトに関してインタビューを受け、解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け講演, 『暇と退屈のポンコツ: 木星に閃光が走った日』, 金曜天文講話, オンライン</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2023-c15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2023-c15/</guid>
      <description>PONCOTSによる木星衝突閃光の観測成功について、一般向けに講演をおこなった。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け講演, 『木星になんかぶつかったんですけど:太陽系を可視動画観測してわかってきたこと』, 第8回宇宙学セミナー, オンライン</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2022-c13/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2022-c13/</guid>
      <description>PONCOTSによる木星衝突閃光の観測成功について、一般の聴講者に向けて講演をおこなった。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け講演, 『OASESとPONCOTS: 影と閃光の動画天文学を創発する』, ガチ天2022, オンライン</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2022-c14-oases-poncots/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2022-c14-oases-poncots/</guid>
      <description>OASESプロジェクトおよびPONCOTSプロジェクトとこれまで得られてきた研究成果について、オンラインイベントにて一般向け講演をおこなった。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け雑誌記事執筆, 『「ポンコツ」機材で史上初観測』月刊星ナビ 2022年11月号, アストロアーツ</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2022-f8/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2022-f8/</guid>
      <description>PONCOTSの観測成果について一般向けの科学雑誌に記事を執筆し、研究成果を紹介・解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での研究プロジェクト解説,『(ぶらっとラボ)最大級の火球、小望遠鏡で』, 朝日新聞</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2022-e27/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2022-e27/</guid>
      <description>PONCOTSの観測成果を含むPONCOTSプロジェクトに関してインタビューを受け、解説し た。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での研究成果解説,『京大の屋上からとらえた木星の希少イベント 「ポンコツ」 装置の挑戦』, 朝日新聞</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2022-e25-2022-10-poncots-30-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2022-e25-2022-10-poncots-30-2022/</guid>
      <description>PONCOTSの観測成果について発表した日本天文学会2022年秋季年会の記者発表にてインタビューを受け、解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での研究成果解説,『京都大学・白眉センター 「ポンコツ」望遠鏡で木星観測』, 日本経済新聞</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2022-e26-2022-10-poncots-30/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2022-e26-2022-10-poncots-30/</guid>
      <description>PONCOTSの観測成果についてインタビューを受け、解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ニュース番組出演・研究成果解説,『今世紀最大の“火球”観測!  木星に小天体が衝突する瞬間 研究のきっかけは「暇だったから」』, フジテレビほかFNN系列</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2022-e21-fnn/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2022-e21-fnn/</guid>
      <description>PONCOTSの観測成果について発表した日本天文学会2022年秋季年会の記者発表にてインタビューを受け、観測成果を解説し、その模様が放送された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での研究成果解説,『木星で最大級の「火球」観測 京大などのグループ、新潟大で発表 』, 新潟日報</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2022-e24/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2022-e24/</guid>
      <description>PONCOTSの観測成果について発表した日本天文学会2022年秋季年会の記者発表にてインタビューを受け、解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>通信社配信記事中での研究成果解説, 『木星で「火球」を観測 今世紀最大か、京大チー ム』, 共同通信</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2022-e22/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2022-e22/</guid>
      <description>PONCOTSの観測成果について発表した日本天文学会2022年秋季年会の記者発表にてイン タビューを受け、解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>通信社配信記事中での研究成果解説, 『木星で今世紀最大の「火球」 30メートルの天体衝突』, 時事通信</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2022-e23-30-2022-9-poncots-30-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2022-e23-30-2022-9-poncots-30-2022/</guid>
      <description>PONCOTSの観測成果について発表した日本天文学会2022年秋季年会の記者発表にてインタビューを受け、解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast optical  flares  from  M  dwarfs  detected  by  a  one-second-cadence  survey  with  Tomo-e  Gozen</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2022-fast-optical-flares-from-m-dwarfs-detected-by-a-one-second-cadence-survey-with-t/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2022-fast-optical-flares-from-m-dwarfs-detected-by-a-one-second-cadence-survey-with-t/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Video  observations  of  tiny  near-Earth  objects  with  Tomo-e  Gozen</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2022-video-observations-of-tiny-near-earth-objects-with-tomo-e-gozen/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2022-video-observations-of-tiny-near-earth-objects-with-tomo-e-gozen/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faint  debris  disk  peering  through  superflare  light echo</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2022-faint-debris-disk-peering-through-superflare-light-echo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2022-faint-debris-disk-peering-through-superflare-light-echo/</guid>
      <description>We present the detectability of strong mid-infrared (MIR) light echoes from faint debris disks illuminated by bright superflares of M-dwarf stars. Circumstellar dust grains around an M-dwarf star are simultaneously heated by superflare radiation. One can thus expect their re-emission in the MIR wavelength regime. According to our model calculations for the Proxima Centauri system, the nearest M-dwarf star system, thermal emission echoes from an inner (r &amp;lt; 1 au) debris disk with a total mass down to that of the solar system’s zodiacal dust are expected to emerge at wavelengths longer than ∼10 μm with a strength comparable to or greater than a white-light superflare. Also, observable echoes from inner- (r ≲ 0.5 au) debris disks irradiated by energetic ( ≳1033.5 erg) superflares of nearby (D &amp;lt; 3 pc) M dwarfs are expected. Our simulation results indicate that superflare monitoring using high-speed optical instruments like OASES and its prompt follow-up using ground-based MIR instruments, such as TAO/MIMIZUKU, can detect these MIR light echoes from debris disks around solar neighborhood flare stars.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>天体写真提供・解説, 『「惑星のパレード」「宇宙は素晴らしい」 石垣島から見える7惑星&amp;月を一枚の写真におさめた写真が話題』, 神戸新聞</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2022-h10-7-2022-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2022-h10-7-2022-6/</guid>
      <description>石垣島にて全太陽系惑星を同時に一枚の画像内に撮影することに成功し、撮影写真が解説付きで掲載された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>天体写真提供・解説, 『一生に一度?奇跡の天体ショー「惑星パレード」とは』, スーパーJ チャンネル, テレビ朝日</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2022-h9-j-2022-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2022-h9-j-2022-6/</guid>
      <description>石垣島にて全太陽系惑星を同時に一枚の画像内に撮影することに成功し、撮影写真が解説付きで報道された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>天体写真提供・解説, 『惑星が直列した瞬間がこれ!』, マイナビニュース</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2022-h11-2022-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2022-h11-2022-6/</guid>
      <description>石垣島にて全太陽系惑星を同時に一枚の画像内に撮影することに成功し、撮影写真が解説付きで掲載された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>天体写真提供・解説, 『明けの空に7惑星集合=月も「共演」―沖縄・石垣島』, 時事通信 ニュース</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2022-h7-7-2022-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2022-h7-7-2022-6/</guid>
      <description>石垣島にて全太陽系惑星を同時に一枚の画像内に撮影することに成功し、撮影写真が解説付きで掲載された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>天体写真提供・解説,『明け方の空に並ぶ惑星 見ごろは6月いっぱい』, 朝日新聞</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2022-h6-6-2022-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2022-h6-6-2022-6/</guid>
      <description>石垣島にて全太陽系惑星を同時に一枚の画像内に撮影することに成功し、撮影写真が解説付きで掲 載された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection  of  an extremely  large  impact  flash  on  Jupiter  by  high-cadence  multiwavelength  observations</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2022-detection-of-an-extremely-large-impact-flash-on-jupiter-by-high-cadence-multiwav/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2022-detection-of-an-extremely-large-impact-flash-on-jupiter-by-high-cadence-multiwav/</guid>
      <description>We report the detection of an optical impact flash on Jupiter on 2021 October 15 by a dedicated telescope, Planetary ObservatioN Camera for Optical Transient Surveys, for the first time. Our temporally resolved three-band observations of the flash allowed investigations of its optical energy without the need for approximations on the impact brightness temperature. The kinetic energy of the impactor was equivalent to approximately two megatons of TNT, an order of magnitude greater than that of previously detected flashes on Jupiter and comparable with the Tunguska impact on Earth in 1908. This detection indicates that Tunguska-like impact events on Jupiter occur approximately once per year, two to three orders of magnitude more frequently than terrestrial impacts. The observed flash displayed a single-temperature blackbody spectrum with an effective temperature of approximately 8300 K without clear temporal variation, possibly representing common radiative features of terrestrial Tunguska-class superbolides.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>天体写真提供・解説,『明けの空に7惑星集合』, 八重山毎日新聞</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2022-h5-7-2022-6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2022-h5-7-2022-6/</guid>
      <description>石垣島にて全太陽系惑星を同時に一枚の画像内に撮影することに成功し、撮影写真が解説付きで掲載された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Simultaneous Limits on Optical Emission from FRB 20190520B by 24.4 fps Observations with Tomo-e Gozen</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2022-deep-simultaneous-limits-on-optical-emission-from-frb-20190520b-by-24-4-fps-obse/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2022-deep-simultaneous-limits-on-optical-emission-from-frb-20190520b-by-24-4-fps-obse/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>天体写真提供・解説, 『気象コーナー』, おきなわHOTeye, NHK沖縄放送局</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-1900-h8-hoteye-nhk/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-1900-h8-hoteye-nhk/</guid>
      <description>石垣島にて全太陽系惑星を同時に一枚の画像内に撮影することに成功し、撮影写真が解説付きで掲載された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery  of  the  Fastest Early Optical Emission from Overluminous SN Ia 2020hvf: A Thermonuclear Explosion within a Dense  Circumstellar  Environment</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2021-discovery-of-the-fastest-early-optical-emission-from-overluminous-sn-ia-2020hvf-/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2021-discovery-of-the-fastest-early-optical-emission-from-overluminous-sn-ia-2020hvf-/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け雑誌記事執筆, 『OASES PONCOTS project 太陽系外縁部の謎に迫る天文学者の挑戦』月刊天文ガイド2022年1月号,  誠文堂新光社</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2021-f7/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2021-f7/</guid>
      <description>一般向けの科学雑誌に記事を執筆し、OASESプロジェクトとPONCOTSプロジェクトのこれまでのあゆみや研究成果について紹介・解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け雑誌記事執筆, 『木星でキラリ！光芒一閃を動画観測で検出』月刊星ナビ 2022年1月号, アストロアーツ</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2021-f6/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2021-f6/</guid>
      <description>2021年10月にPONCOTSで観測に成功した木星衝突閃光について一般向けの科学雑誌に記事を執筆し、 研究成果を紹介・解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け講演,  『太陽系グランドツアー』, 京都大学 岡山天文台 オンライン特別公開, オンライン</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2021-c12-2021-11-oases-poncots/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2021-c12-2021-11-oases-poncots/</guid>
      <description>太陽系の概説およびOASESプロジェクトおよびPONCOTSプロジェクトとこれまで得られてきた研 究成果について、オンラインイベントにて一般向け講演をおこなった。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け雑誌記事執筆, 『10月15日の木星衝突閃光をとらえた』月刊天文ガイド 2021年12月号, 誠文堂新光社</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2021-f5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2021-f5/</guid>
      <description>2021年10月にPONCOTSで観測に成功した木星衝突閃光について一般向けの科学雑誌に記事を執筆し、 研究成果を紹介・解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ニュース番組出演・研究成果解説, 『木星で発光現象 約3秒間強く輝く 隕石落下か 京都大 天文台』, NHK, NHKニュース7</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2021-e20-3-nhk-nhk-7-2021-10-2021-poncots/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2021-e20-3-nhk-nhk-7-2021-10-2021-poncots/</guid>
      <description>2021年にPONCOTSで観測に成功した木星衝突閃光についてインタビューを受け、観測成果を解説し、その模様が放送された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向けweb記事執筆, 『史上9例目、木星表面の衝突閃光をとらえた』アストロアーツWEBニュース, アストロアーツ</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2021-f4-9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2021-f4-9/</guid>
      <description>2021年にPONCOTSで観測に成功した木星衝突閃光について一般向けの科学webニュースサイトに 記事を執筆し、紹介・解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け講義,  『太陽系の地図の余白から 太陽系外縁天体の世界』, 朝日カルチャーセンター 横浜教室 『太陽系ー謎に満ちた天体に迫る』, 朝日カルチャーセンター横浜教室(神奈川県横浜市)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2021-c11-cid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2021-c11-cid/</guid>
      <description>太陽系外縁天体の概論とOASESの成果を含む最新の研究結果について、一般の聴講者に向けて講義をおこなった。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け講演,『オールトの雲へ ̶小望遠鏡が太陽系の果てを解明する日』, 金曜天文講話, オンライン</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2021-c10-2021-5-oases/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2021-c10-2021-5-oases/</guid>
      <description>OASESプロジェクトによるカイパーベルト小天体検出について、一般向けに講演をおこなった。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detectability of Optical Transients with Timescales of Subseconds</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2021-detectability-of-optical-transients-with-timescales-of-subseconds/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2021-detectability-of-optical-transients-with-timescales-of-subseconds/</guid>
      <description>We search for optical transient sources with durations of ∼0.1 to ∼1.3 s using a data set obtained in the Organized Autotelescopes for Serendipitous Event Survey (OASES) observation campaign. Since the OASES observations were carried out using two independent wide-field and high-cadence observation systems monitored the same field simultaneously, the obtained data set provides a unique opportunity to develop a robust detection method for subsecond optical transients. In the data set of a selected field around the ecliptic and the Galactic plane, we find no astronomical event candidate that satisfies our detection criteria. From the nondetection result, we derive an upper limit on the event rate of subsecond transients around the ecliptic and the Galactic plane for the first time, obtaining ∼0.090 and ∼0.38 hr−1 deg−2 for m = 12 and 13 Vmag, respectively. In addition, future prospects of the subsecond-scale transient event surveys are discussed.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An  optical  search  for  transients  lasting  a  few  seconds</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2020-an-optical-search-for-transients-lasting-a-few-seconds/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2020-an-optical-search-for-transients-lasting-a-few-seconds/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relationship between Radar Cross Section and Optical Magnitude based on Radar and Optical Simultaneous Observations of Faint Meteors</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2020-relationship-between-radar-cross-section-and-optical-magnitude-based-on-radar-an/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2020-relationship-between-radar-cross-section-and-optical-magnitude-based-on-radar-an/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>科学イラスト提供, 『星をみつめて 京大花山天文台から』(書籍), 京都新聞出版センター</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2020-h4-2020-12-cg/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2020-h4-2020-12-cg/</guid>
      <description>太陽系外縁部に存在する小天体のCGイラストが、書籍中の採用された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け講演, 『拡がる太陽系 -はやぶさ2・ネオワイズ彗星・宮古島-』,  金曜天文講話, オンライン</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2020-c9/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2020-c9/</guid>
      <description>OASESプロジェクトによるカイパーベルト小天体検出を含む太陽系小天体の話題について、一般向 けに講演をおこなった。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け雑誌記事執筆, 『またたく宇宙をつかまえる〈後編〉 アマチュア天文学の未来』, 月刊星ナビ 2020年8月号, アストロアーツ</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2020-f3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2020-f3/</guid>
      <description>OASESによるカイパーベルト小天体検出について一般向けの科学雑誌に記事を執筆し、研 究成果を紹介・解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での研究成果解説,  『冥王星 大気薄くなる 京大など観測』, 読売新聞</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2020-e19-2020-6-cid/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2020-e19-2020-6-cid/</guid>
      <description>冥王星大気に関する掩蔽観測成果についてインタビューを受け、研究成果を解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence  for  a  rapid  decrease  of  Plutoʼs  atmospheric  pressure  revealed  by  a  stellar occultation in 2019</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2020-evidence-for-a-rapid-decrease-of-pluto-s-atmospheric-pressure-revealed-by-a-stel/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2020-evidence-for-a-rapid-decrease-of-pluto-s-atmospheric-pressure-revealed-by-a-stel/</guid>
      <description>We report observations of a stellar occultation by Pluto on 2019 July 17. A single-chord high-speed (time resolution = 2 s) photometry dataset was obtained with a CMOS camera mounted on the Tohoku University 60 cm telescope (Haleakala, Hawaii). The occultation light curve is satisfactorily fitted to an existing atmospheric model of Pluto. We find the lowest pressure value at a reference radius of r = 1215 km among those reported after 2012. These reports indicate a possible rapid (approximately 21−5+4% of the previous value) pressure drop between 2016, which is the latest reported estimate, and 2019. However, this drop is detected at a 2.4σ level only and still requires confirmation from future observations. If real, this trend is opposite from the monotonic increase of Pluto’s atmospheric pressure reported by previous studies. The observed decrease trend is possibly caused by ongoing N2 condensation processes in the Sputnik Planitia glacier associated with an orbitally driven decline of solar insolation, as predicted by previous theoretical models. However, the observed amplitude of the pressure decrease is larger than the model predictions.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け雑誌記事執筆, 『またたく宇宙をつかまえる〈前編〉 360万円でEKBO発見』, 月刊星ナビ 2020年6月号, アストロアーツ</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2020-f2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2020-f2/</guid>
      <description>OASESによるカイパーベルト小天体検出について一般向けの科学雑誌に記事を執筆し、研 究成果を紹介・解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>科学イラスト提供, 表紙イラスト, 月刊星ナビ 2020年6月号, アストロアーツ</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2020-h3-2020-6-2020-5-oases-f2-cg/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2020-h3-2020-6-2020-5-oases-f2-cg/</guid>
      <description>OASESプロジェクトに関する雑誌特集記事の内容に合わせて太陽系外縁部に存在する小天体のCGイラストを作成し、雑誌表紙に採用された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Luminosity  Function  of  Faint  Sporadic  Meteors  measured  with  a  Wide-Field  CMOS  mosaic camera Tomo-e PM</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2019-luminosity-function-of-faint-sporadic-meteors-measured-with-a-wide-field-cmos-mo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2019-luminosity-function-of-faint-sporadic-meteors-measured-with-a-wide-field-cmos-mo/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での研究成果解説,  『科学の扉 動画が天文学変える』, 朝日新聞</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e18-2019-12-oases-22/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e18-2019-12-oases-22/</guid>
      <description>OASESの観測成果、および太陽系外縁天体(50000) Quaoarによる恒星掩蔽観測成果についてインタビューを受け、 研究成果の解説をした。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New  constraint  on  the  atmosphere  of  (50000)  Quaoar  from  a  stellar occultation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2019-new-constraint-on-the-atmosphere-of-50000-quaoar-from-a-stellar-occultation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2019-new-constraint-on-the-atmosphere-of-50000-quaoar-from-a-stellar-occultation/</guid>
      <description>We report observations of a stellar occultation by the classical Kuiper Belt object (50000) Quaoar that occurred on 2019 June 28. A single-chord high-cadence (2 Hz) photometry data set was obtained with the Tomo-e Gozen CMOS camera mounted on the 1.05 m Schmidt telescope at Kiso Observatory. The obtained ingress and egress data do not show any indication of atmospheric refraction and allow new 1σ and 3σ upper limits of 6 and 16 nbar, respectively, to be set for the surface pressure of a pure methane atmosphere. These upper limits are lower than the saturation vapor pressure of methane at Quaoar’s expected mean surface temperature (T ∼ 44 K) and imply the absence of a ∼10 nbar-level global atmosphere formed by methane ice on Quaoar’s surface.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け講演, 『太陽系の果て、マジでヤバい』, 花山星空ネットワーク 第23回 講演会, 京 都大学 理学研究科セミナーハウス(京都府京都市)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2019-c8/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2019-c8/</guid>
      <description>OASESプロジェクトによるカイパーベルト小天体検出について、一般向けに招待講演をおこなった。&amp;quot;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向けweb記事執筆, 『太陽系の果てに小天体の影を発見したのは、宮古島の小さな望遠鏡だった - 半径約 1.3kmのカイパーベルト天体を初観測』, academist Journal, アカデミスト</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2019-f1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/f-2019-f1/</guid>
      <description>OASESによるカイパーベルト小天体検出について一般向けの科学webニュースサイトに記事を執筆し、研究成果を紹介・解説した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>テレビ番組出演, コズミックフロント☆NEXT, NHKBSプレミアム</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e17-next-nhkbs-2019-4-oases-22/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e17-next-nhkbs-2019-4-oases-22/</guid>
      <description>OASESによるカイパーベルト小天体検出について観測地である宮古島での現地取材対応を おこない、観測プロジェクトや研究成果について紹介し、その模様が放送された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>雑誌記事中での研究成果解説, “Astronomers Traverse the Globe to Shadow “Lucky Stars””, Scientific American</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e15-astronomers-traverse-the-globe-to-shadow-lucky-stars-scientific-american-201/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e15-astronomers-traverse-the-globe-to-shadow-lucky-stars-scientific-american-201/</guid>
      <description>OASESによるカイパーベルト小天体検出についてインタビューを受け、研究成果の解説をした(英文記事)。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>雑誌記事中での研究成果解説, ”Mysterious &#39;Missing Link&#39; Object Found At Edge Of Solar System By Scientists Using Tiny Telescopes”, Forbes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e13-mysterious-missing-link-object-found-at-edge-of-solar-system-by-scientists-u/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e13-mysterious-missing-link-object-found-at-edge-of-solar-system-by-scientists-u/</guid>
      <description>OASESによるカイパーベルト小天体検出についてインタビューを受け、研究成果の解説をし た(英文記事)。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ニュース番組出演・研究成果解説, 『低予算で大発見!太陽系の “最果て” に小天体 日本の研究者』, NHK NHKニュース おはよう日本</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e6-nhk-nhk-2019-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e6-nhk-nhk-2019-1/</guid>
      <description>OASESによるカイパーベルト小天体検出についてインタビュー対応をおこない、その模様が放送された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A kilometre-sized Kuiper belt object discovered by stellar occultation using amateur telescopes</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2019-a-kilometre-sized-kuiper-belt-object-discovered-by-stellar-occultation-using-ama/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2019-a-kilometre-sized-kuiper-belt-object-discovered-by-stellar-occultation-using-ama/</guid>
      <description>Kuiper belt objects (KBOs) are thought to be remnants of the early Solar System, and their size distribution provides an opportunity to explore the formation and evolution of the outer Solar System1,2,3,4,5. In particular, the size distribution of kilometre-sized (radius = 1–10 km) KBOs represents a signature of initial planetesimal sizes when planets form5. These kilometre-sized KBOs are extremely faint, and it is impossible to detect them directly. Instead, the monitoring of stellar occultation events is one possible way to discover these small KBOs6,7,8,9. However, until now, there has been no observational evidence for occultation events of KBOs with radii of 1–10 km. Here, we report the first detection of a single occultation event candidate by a KBO with a radius of ~1.3 km, which was simultaneously provided by two low-cost small telescopes coupled with commercial complementary metal–oxide–semiconductor cameras. From this detection, we conclude that the surface number density of KBOs with radii exceeding ~1.2 km is ~6 × 105 deg−2. This surface number density favours a theoretical size distribution model with an excess signature at a radius of 1–2 km (ref. 5). If this is a true KBO detection, this implies that planetesimals before their runaway growth phase grew into kilometre-sized objects in the primordial outer Solar System and remain as a major population in the present-day Kuiper belt.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での研究成果解説,  『太陽から50億キロ 微小天体初観測』, 日本経済新聞</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e10-50-2019-1-oases-22/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e10-50-2019-1-oases-22/</guid>
      <description>OASESによるカイパーベルト小天体検出についてインタビューを受け、研究成果の解説をした。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での研究成果解説,  『太陽系の果てに微小天体 直径2.6キロ「彗星の赤ちゃん」か』, 産経新聞</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e11-2-6-2019-1-oases-22/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e11-2-6-2019-1-oases-22/</guid>
      <description>OASESによるカイパーベルト小天体検出についてインタビューを受け、研究成果の解説をし た。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での研究成果解説,  『市販望遠鏡で太陽系の果て観測 50億km離れた半径1.3kmの天体』, 毎日新聞</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e9-50-km-1-3km-2019-1-oases-22/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e9-50-km-1-3km-2019-1-oases-22/</guid>
      <description>OASESによるカイパーベルト小天体検出についてインタビューを受け、研究成果の解説をした。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での研究成果解説, 『太陽系の最果てに小天体の“影”観測』, しんぶん赤旗</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e12-2019-1-oases-22/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e12-2019-1-oases-22/</guid>
      <description>OASESによるカイパーベルト小天体検出についてインタビューを受け、研究成果の解説をした。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>通信社配信記事中での研究成果解説,  『最果ての微小天体、初観測 市販望遠鏡で世界に先行』, 共同通信</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e7/</guid>
      <description>OASESによるカイパーベルト小天体検出についてインタビューを受け、研究成果の解説をし た。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>通信社配信記事中での研究成果解説,  『太陽系外縁の小天体観測=沖縄から望遠鏡で−国立天文台など』,  時事通信</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e8-2019-1-oases-22/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2019-e8-2019-1-oases-22/</guid>
      <description>OASESによるカイパーベルト小天体検出についてインタビューを受け、研究成果の解説をした。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluation  of  large  pixel  CMOS  image  sensors  for  the  Tomo-e Gozen wide field camera</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2018-evaluation-of-large-pixel-cmos-image-sensors-for-the-tomo-e-gozen-wide-field-cam/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2018-evaluation-of-large-pixel-cmos-image-sensors-for-the-tomo-e-gozen-wide-field-cam/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The  Tomo-e  Gozen  wide  field  CMOS  camera  for  the  Kiso Schmidt telescope</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2018-the-tomo-e-gozen-wide-field-cmos-camera-for-the-kiso-schmidt-telescope/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2018-the-tomo-e-gozen-wide-field-cmos-camera-for-the-kiso-schmidt-telescope/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advantages  of  the  Akari  FIR  All-Sky  Maps</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2017-advantages-of-the-akari-fir-all-sky-maps/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2017-advantages-of-the-akari-fir-all-sky-maps/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FIR  View of Disks of Weak-Line T Tauri Stars</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2017-fir-view-of-disks-of-weak-line-t-tauri-stars/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2017-fir-view-of-disks-of-weak-line-t-tauri-stars/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small-Scale  Structure  of  the  Zodiacal  Dust  Cloud  Observed  in  Far- Infrared  with  Akari</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2017-small-scale-structure-of-the-zodiacal-dust-cloud-observed-in-far-infrared-with-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2017-small-scale-structure-of-the-zodiacal-dust-cloud-observed-in-far-infrared-with-a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>特集番組出演および番組制作協力, 『OASES 氷小天体を探せ』, 宮古テレビ, MTVサンデー トピック</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2017-e5-oases-mtv-2017-11-oases/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2017-e5-oases-mtv-2017-11-oases/</guid>
      <description>OASESプロジェクトの観測についての特集番組制作にあたり、観測時やイベント実施時の取材に対 応したほか、インタビュー動画で出演し、サイエンス内容などの解説をおこなった。また観測システムによって得られた動画のデータや観測時に撮影した天体写真を提供した。さらに応募者が主催したひらめき☆ときめきサイエンス事業『宮古島宇宙学校』について現地での取材とインタビューに対応し、その模様が放送された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cold Molecular Gas Along the Merger Sequence in Local Luminous Infrared Galaxies</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2017-cold-molecular-gas-along-the-merger-sequence-in-local-luminous-infrared-galaxies/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2017-cold-molecular-gas-along-the-merger-sequence-in-local-luminous-infrared-galaxies/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ニュース番組出演, 『研究最前線を学ぶ 宮古島宇宙学校』, RBC NEWS, RBC琉球放送</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2017-e4-rbc-news-rbc-2017-8-d1/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2017-e4-rbc-news-rbc-2017-8-d1/</guid>
      <description>主催したひらめき☆ときめきサイエンス事業『宮古島宇宙学校』について現地での取材とインタビューに対応し、その模様が放送された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>平成29年度, 科学研究費助成事業, ひらめき☆ときめき サイエンス〜ようこそ大学の研究室へ〜KAKENHI, 『宮古島宇宙学校:宮古島から宇宙を探ろう』</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/d-2017-kakenhi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/d-2017-kakenhi/</guid>
      <description>当該事業を企画・主催し、代表者を務め、プログラムの作成・実行を担当した。本イベントには現地の高校生が参加し、最新の天文学に関する講義を実施したほか、OASES観測システムを使用した観測体験実習を実施。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>市長表敬訪問および市長・市幹部向け講演, 宮古島市長表敬訪問, 宮古島市役所(沖縄県宮古島市)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2017-c5-2017-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2017-c5-2017-7/</guid>
      <description>宮古島で実施しているOASESプロジェクトについて報告するとともに、市長を含む市長部局の所属幹部向けに今後得られる科学成果等について講演した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Organized  Autotelescopes  for  Serendipitous  Event  Survey  (OASES):  Design  and  performance</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2017-organized-autotelescopes-for-serendipitous-event-survey-oases-design-and-perform/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2017-organized-autotelescopes-for-serendipitous-event-survey-oases-design-and-perform/</guid>
      <description>Organized Autotelescopes for Serendipitous Event Survey (OASES) is an optical observation project that aims to detect and investigate stellar occultation events by kilometer-sized trans-Neptunian objects (TNOs). In this project, multiple low-cost observation systems for wide-field and high-speed photometry were developed in order to detect rare and short-timescale stellar occultation events. The observation system consists of commercial off-the-shelf 0.28 m aperture f/1.58 optics providing a 2.3 deg × 1.8 deg field of view. A commercial CMOS camera is coupled to the optics to obtain full-frame imaging with a frame rate greater than 10 Hz. As of 2016 September, this project exploits two observation systems, which are installed on Miyako Island, Okinawa, Japan. Recent improvements in CMOS technology in terms of high-speed imaging and low readout noise mean that the observation systems are capable of monitoring ∼2000 stars in the Galactic plane simultaneously with magnitudes down to V ∼ 13.0, providing ∼20% photometric precision in light curves with a sampling cadence of 15.4 Hz. This number of monitored stars is larger than for any other existing instruments for coordinated occultation surveys. In addition, a precise time synchronization method needed for simultaneous occultation detection is developed using faint meteors. The two OASES observation systems are executing coordinated monitoring observations of a dense stellar field in order to detect occultations by kilometer-sized TNOs for the first time.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での研究解説,  『氷小天体を探せ 若手研究者「オアシズ」 宮古島市 で観測挑戦』, 琉球新報</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2017-e3-2017-7-oases/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2017-e3-2017-7-oases/</guid>
      <description>OASESプロジェクトの観測について現地にて取材に対応し、サイエンス内容などの解説をおこなっ た。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ニュース番組出演・解説, 『宮古島で氷小天体の発見目指す』, RBC NEWS, RBC琉球放送</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2017-e2-rbc-news-rbc-2017-6-oases/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2017-e2-rbc-news-rbc-2017-6-oases/</guid>
      <description>宮古島でのOASESプロジェクトの観測について現地にてインタビュー対応をおこない、その模様が放送された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>新聞記事中での研究解説,『「氷小惑星」の発見目指す/天体観測PJ』, 宮古毎日新聞</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2017-e1-pj-2017-6-oases/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/e-2017-e1-pj-2017-6-oases/</guid>
      <description>宮古島でのOASESプロジェクトの観測について現地にて取材に対応し、サイエンス内容などの解説をおこなった。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>天体写真提供,『宇宙はなぜ「暗い」のか』(書籍, 著: 津村 耕司), 新星出版</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2017-h2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2017-h2/</guid>
      <description>宮古島で撮影した天の川の画像が、書籍中の銀河面の説明画像として採用された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AKARI  far-infrared  maps  of the  zodiacal  dust  bands</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-akari-far-infrared-maps-of-the-zodiacal-dust-bands/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-akari-far-infrared-maps-of-the-zodiacal-dust-bands/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け講演, 『月と宇宙のはなし』, 星空観察会 ~スーパームーンまで・星空散歩, 沖縄県立 宮古青少年の家(沖縄県宮古島市)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2016-c4-2016-11-oases/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2016-c4-2016-11-oases/</guid>
      <description>OASES観測施設である沖縄県立宮古青少年の家にて実施された小中学生と保護者向けの天体観測イベントにて、月を中心とした太陽系に関する講演をおこなった。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>高校生向け講義, 『宮古島での天体観測プロジェクトについて』, 地学特別授業, 沖縄県立宮 古高校(沖縄県宮古島市)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2016-c3-2016-11-oases/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2016-c3-2016-11-oases/</guid>
      <description>OASESプロジェクトの観測地である宮古島市内の高校にて地学授業の特別講師をつとめ、天文学に 関する講義とOASESプロジェクトの紹介をおこなった。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Development  of  a  prototype  of  the  Tomo-e  Gozen  wide-field  CMOS  camera</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-development-of-a-prototype-of-the-tomo-e-gozen-wide-field-cmos-camera/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-development-of-a-prototype-of-the-tomo-e-gozen-wide-field-cmos-camera/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Development  of  a  real-time  data  processing  system  for  a  prototype  of  the  Tomo-e Gozen  wide  field  CMOS  camera</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-development-of-a-real-time-data-processing-system-for-a-prototype-of-the-tomo-e-/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2016-development-of-a-real-time-data-processing-system-for-a-prototype-of-the-tomo-e-/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>中学生向け講義, 『日食と宮古島で明らかにする宇宙』, 特別授業, 宮古島市立久松中学校(沖 縄県宮古島市)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2016-c2-2016-3-oases/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2016-c2-2016-3-oases/</guid>
      <description>OASESプロジェクトの観測地である宮古島市内の中学校にて、部分日食にあわせて実施された特別授業で生徒に向けた講演を実施した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calibration  of the AKARI far-infrared all-sky survey maps</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2015-calibration-of-the-akari-far-infrared-all-sky-survey-maps/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2015-calibration-of-the-akari-far-infrared-all-sky-survey-maps/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>一般向け講演,『宮古島OASESプロジェクトについて』, ありんこ文庫おしゃべり会, Book Cafe BREATHE(沖縄県宮古島市)</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2015-c1-oases-book-cafe-breathe-2015-10-oases/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/c-2015-c1-oases-book-cafe-breathe-2015-10-oases/</guid>
      <description>OASESプロジェクトの観測地である宮古島市での地元住民向けの講演会および意見交換会を企画・ 実施した。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The  AKARI  far-infrared  all-sky  survey  maps</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2015-the-akari-far-infrared-all-sky-survey-maps/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2015-the-akari-far-infrared-all-sky-survey-maps/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kiso  Supernova  Survey  (KISS):  Survey  strategy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2014-kiso-supernova-survey-kiss-survey-strategy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2014-kiso-supernova-survey-kiss-survey-strategy/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Point source calibration of the AKARI/FIS all- sky  survey  maps  for  stacking  analysis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2014-point-source-calibration-of-the-akari-fis-all-sky-survey-maps-for-stacking-analy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 Dec 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2014-point-source-calibration-of-the-akari-fis-all-sky-survey-maps-for-stacking-analy/</guid>
      <description>Investigations of the point spread functions (PSFs) and flux calibrations for stacking analysis have been performed with the far-infrared (wavelength range of 60 to 140 μm) all-sky maps taken by the Far-Infrared Surveyor (FIS) on board the AKARI satellite. The PSFs are investigated by stacking the maps at the positions of standard stars with their fluxes of 0.02–10 Jy. The derived full widths at the half maximum (FWHMs) of the PSFs are ∼ 60′′ at 65 and 90 μm and ∼ 90′′ at 140 μm, which are much smaller than those of the previous all-sky maps obtained with the Infrared Astronomical Satellite IRAS (∼ 6′). Any flux dependence in the PSFs is not seen on the investigated flux range. By performing the flux calibrations, we found that absolute photometry for faint sources can be carried out with constant calibration factors, which range from 0.6 to 0.8. After applying the calibration factors, the photometric accuracies for the stacked sources in the 65, 90, and 140 μm bands are 9%, 3%, and 21%, respectively, even below the detection limits of the survey. No systematic dependence between the observed flux and model flux is found. These results indicate that the FIS map is a useful dataset for the stacking analyses of faint sources at far-infrared wavelengths.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Near-infrared Brightness  of  Ganymede  and  Callisto  Eclipsed  in  Jovian  Shadow:  A  New  Scope  to  Investigate Jovian Upper Atmosphere</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2014-near-infrared-brightness-of-ganymede-and-callisto-eclipsed-in-jovian-shadow-a-ne/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2014-near-infrared-brightness-of-ganymede-and-callisto-eclipsed-in-jovian-shadow-a-ne/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiwavelength study of the high-latitude cloud L1642: chain of star formation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2014-multiwavelength-study-of-the-high-latitude-cloud-l1642-chain-of-star-formation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Apr 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2014-multiwavelength-study-of-the-high-latitude-cloud-l1642-chain-of-star-formation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AKARI North Ecliptic Pole Deep Survey. Revision of the catalogue via a new image analysis</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/paper-7/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/paper-7/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interstellar  Dust  Properties  of  M51  from  AKARI  Mid-infrared  Images</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2013-interstellar-dust-properties-of-m51-from-akari-mid-infrared-images/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2013-interstellar-dust-properties-of-m51-from-akari-mid-infrared-images/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>天体写真提供・解説, 『宮古の空に彗星 東大生有松さん撮影』, 琉球新報</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2011-h1-2013-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/outreach/h-2011-h1-2013-3/</guid>
      <description>近日点通過直後、超低空に位置していたパンスターズ彗星(C/2011 L4 PanSTARRS)の撮影に成功し、撮影写真が解説付きで紙面に掲載された。</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Search for Infrared Emission from Core-collapse Supernovae  at  the  Transitional  Phase</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2012-a-search-for-infrared-emission-from-core-collapse-supernovae-at-the-transitional/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2012-a-search-for-infrared-emission-from-core-collapse-supernovae-at-the-transitional/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AKARI  Far-Infrared  All-Sky  Survey  Maps</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2012-akari-far-infrared-all-sky-survey-maps/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2012-akari-far-infrared-all-sky-survey-maps/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interstellar  Dust  in  M51  from  IRC  Images</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2012-interstellar-dust-in-m51-from-irc-images/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2012-interstellar-dust-in-m51-from-irc-images/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Filamentary Web of Star Formation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2012-the-filamentary-web-of-star-formation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2012-the-filamentary-web-of-star-formation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization and Improvement  of  the  Image  Quality  of  the  Data  Taken  with  the  Infrared  Camera  (IRC)  Mid- Infrared  Channels  onboard  AKARI</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2011-characterization-and-improvement-of-the-image-quality-of-the-data-taken-with-the/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2011-characterization-and-improvement-of-the-image-quality-of-the-data-taken-with-the/</guid>
      <description>Mid-infrared images frequently suffer artifacts and extended point-spread functions (PSFs). We investigate the characteristics of the artifacts and the PSFs in images obtained with the infrared camera (IRC) on board AKARI at four mid-infrared bands of the S7 (7 μm), S11 (11 μm), L15 (15 μm), and L24 (24 μm). Removal of the artifacts significantly improves the reliability of the reference data for flat-fielding at the L15 and L24 bands. A set of models of the IRC PSFs is also constructed from on-orbit data. These PSFs have extended components that come from diffraction and scattering within the detector arrays. We estimate the aperture correction factors for point sources and the surface brightness correction factors for diffuse sources. We conclude that the surface brightness correction factors range from 0.95 to 0.8, taking account of the extended component of the PSFs. To correct for the extended PSF effects for the study of faint structures, we also develop an image reconstruction method, which consists of the deconvolution with the PSF and the convolution with an appropriate Gaussian. The appropriate removal of the artifacts, improved flat-fielding, and image reconstruction with the extended PSFs enable us to investigate detailed structures of extended sources in IRC mid-infrared images.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection  of  the  Detached  Dust  Shell  of  U  Antliae  at  Mid-infrared  Wavelengths  with AKARI/IRC</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/publications/2011-detection-of-the-detached-dust-shell-of-u-antliae-at-mid-infrared-wavelengths-wi/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/publications/2011-detection-of-the-detached-dust-shell-of-u-antliae-at-mid-infrared-wavelengths-wi/</guid>
      <description>We report mid-infrared (MIR) imaging observations of the carbon star U Ant made with the Infrared Camera (IRC) on board AKARI. Subtraction of the artifacts and extended point-spread function of the central star reveals the detached dust shell around the carbon star at MIR wavelengths (15 and 24 μm) for the first time. The observed radial brightness profiles of the MIR emission are well explained by two shells at 43″ and 50″ from the central star detected in optical scattered light observations. Combining Herschel/PACS, AKARI/FIS, and AKARI/IRC data, we obtain the infrared spectral energy distribution (SED) of the thermal emission from the detached shell of U Ant in a wide infrared spectral range of 15–160 μm. Thermal emission of amorphous carbon grains with a single temperature cannot account for the observed SED from 15 to 160 μm: it underestimates the emission at 15 μm. Alternatively, the observed SED is fitted by the model in which amorphous carbon grains in the two shells have different temperatures of 60 and 104 K, which allocates most dust mass in the shell at 50″. This supports the previous suggestion that the 43″ shell is gas-rich and the 50″ shell is dust-rich. We suggest a possibility that the segregation of the gas and dust resulting from the drift motion of submicron-sized dust grains relative to the gas and that the hot dust component associated with the gas-rich shell is composed of very small grains that are strongly coupled with the gas.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
